TRAVIS A. GREEN

Richardson, TX linkedin.com/in/travis-green-mpa-23b77a125/

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Candidate in Public Affairs, the University of Texas at Dallas Masters of Public Affairs, the University of Texas at Dallas, 2020 Graduate Certificate in Local Government Management B.S. Information Technology, Capella University, Cum laude, 2016 B.S Economics, the University of Utah, 2005

SUMMARY

Assistant Fire Chief with twenty years of management experience. Current responsibilities include the management of the Fire Marshal's Office, Emergency Medical Services, and fire department personnel. In the absence of the fire chief, function as the administrative authority of the department and provide command presence during emergency events when needed.

PROFESSIONAL HISTORY

April 2007 – Present Fairview, TX

Assistant Fire Chief January 2020 - present

- Responsible for fire department personnel
- Project lead for implementing Fairview's first Human Resource Information System (HRIS), NEOGOV.
- Committee member on a town-wide compensation and evaluation study, including selecting the consulting firm and implementing the project outcome.
- Started the Fairview Fire Marshals' office as a Texas Commission on Law Enforcement entity.

Additionally, I am responsible for department personnel. This includes hiring, coaching, satisfaction assessment, and disciplinary actions as needed. Act as the department EMS Administrator responsible for ambulance and EMS service regulatory compliance for the department. Function as the liaison between the police department and fire department regarding Active Shooter and Hostile Event (ASHE) response and training.

Fire Marshal/Battalion Chief January 2017 - January 2020

Directed the activities and operations of the Fire Marshal's Office; provided professional, technical, and administrative support to the Fire Chief and performs related duties. Function as a licensed peace officer and performs related work as required. Responsible for criminal and non-criminal investigations regarding fires and explosions. Oversaw the life safety and fire prevention programs, plan review, commercial and residential inspections as well as fire and explosive investigations.

Fire Department Captain/ EMS Administrator April 2010 - December 2016

- Provided EMS administration including contract negotiation, quality assurance evaluations, training and medical control management.
- Headed the transition from private ambulance service through AMR to department-run EMS transport.
- Functioned as the department's Acting Chief and Fire Marshal when the Fire Chief was out of town.
- Participated on hiring panel for various positions in the organization

Acted as the department EMS Captain responsible for ambulance and EMS services for the department. During 2015, I managed the transition from a contracted private ambulance transport service to in-house ambulance staffing.

Part-Time Firefighter January 2007 – April 2010

Worked half-time for the Fairview Fire Department as a firefighter paramedic. Performed a variety of tasks involving and/or related to fire suppression and emergency medical services.

Town of Prosper August 2008 - April 2010 Prosper, TX Firefighter Paramedic

Performed a variety of highly technical and specialized tasks involving and/or related to fire suppression, emergency medical services, rescue, hazardous materials incidents, fire prevention, fire inspections, administration, and other special assignments as required. Supervised and controlled emergency medical scenes until relieved by a higher ranking officer. Performed other duties as assigned.

Coveted Marketing LLC April 2004 – 2013 Fairview, TX Owner/Founder

Manage the day-to-day operations of an online survey research business. Developed web-based survey tools and websites for clients. Provided reports to corporate communications and human resource departments on employee sentiment and management feedback. Supervise a team of three contractors who develop online surveys, provide custom web development, analyze data, and write reports based on

findings. Interacted with an open-source community for the phpsurveyor.com application and modified PHP code as needed for projects.

Pixo, Inc October 2001 - April 2003 San Jose, CA Internet Product Manager

Worked closely with the engineering team to develop a wireless e-commerce Internet server product name Pixo Download Server that Sun Microsystems later acquired. Helped develop feature set, security model, pricing, positioning, and marketing requirement plans (MRDs). Responsible for the Internet developer program for mini "pixlet" web content applications that run on Pixo OS. Managed the pixo.com website to support company products.

Netscape/America Online December 1999 - October 2001 Mountain View, CA Internet Program Manager

Managed daily operations of Netcenter.com's Personal Finance and Business Channel with a combined \$10 million in revenues. Responsibilities included providing content, and site layout, monitoring the channel's performance, and integrating input from various engineering, legal, and business teams. In addition, I managed the revenue goals for content providers and advertising.

Bank One December 1997 - December 1999 Chicago, IL Product Manager/ Online Trade Desk Manager

Responsible for layout and content on the Bank One Securities brokerage website. Acted as one of the principal team members that launched Wingspan Bank. Worked on the team that developed Wingspan's online brokerage website from concept to launch—managed online brokerage trade team.

Fidelity Investments June 1995 - December 1997 Salt Lake City, UT Senior Trader Online Brokerage

Interfaced with the electronics product group as a team member, helping to design the layout and functionality of the initial online brokerage offering, WebXpress. Extensive knowledge of financial services, including trading Equities, Fixed Income, International pdfSecurities, and Options. Held Security Series 4,6,7, and 8 licenses.

ORGANIZATION MEMBERSHIPS AND AFFILIATIONS

Member American Society for Public Administration (ASPA)

Member International City Management Association (ICMA)

Member of the Urban Management Assistants of North Texas (UMANT)

Treasurer for the Collin County Fire Investigation Association 501 (C) (3)

Member of the National Association of Fire Prevention (NFPA)

Member of the National Association of Fire Investigators (NAFI)

Member of the North Texas Firemen's and Fire Marshals' Association

Member of the Texas Municipal Police Association (TMPA)

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

Green, T.A (June 2006). The Importance of Automatic External Defibrillators (AEDs) and CPR. Presented at the Lovejov School District Yearly Faculty Conference.

Green, T.A (April 2015). Fairview EMS Kickoff, Fairview Town News Magazine

Green, T.A (April 2016). Fairview EMS First Anniversary, *Fairview Town News Magazine*

Green, T.A (August 2015). Heritage Ranch Emergency Medical Services Presentation. Presented at the Heritage Ranch Country Club 2015 Speaker Presentation Series.

ADDITIONAL SKILLS AND TRAINING

TCFP Advanced Firefighter, Driver Operator, Fire Officer II, Instructor II

TCFP Advanced Inspector and Arson Investigator

TCFP Ropes and Trench Technician, Safety Officer

TDSHS Licensed Paramedic

TCOLE Peace Officer

2018 Forensic Fire Death Class at Sam Houston State University

2017 IAAI Cause and Origin Course

TEEX Incident Command System for High-Rise Operations

National Fire Academy Command and Control Course

North Texas Fire Marshal's Conference Attendee 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020

CFI Trainer Courses: ARC Mapping, Investigating Fatal Fires, Managing Complex Fire

Scene Investigations, Post Flashover Fires, Process of Elimination, The Impact of

Ventilation in Building Structures on Fire Development

Fire Engineering Course Dead Men Do Tell Tales

ALERRT Active Attack Integrated Response (AAIR) Instructor

ALERRT CRASE (Citizens Response to Active Shooter Events) Instructor

ALERRT Active Shooter Incident Management (ASIM) course

Tri-County Auto Task Force Auto Theft Recognition and Apprehension Course

Fast Start in Project Management

CompTIA - Network+ certification